Register of the Woman's Relief Corps (U.S.). Dept. of Wisconsin: Records, 1883-1984
Wisconsin Historical Society
Woman's Relief Corps (U.S.). Dept. of Wisconsin: Records, 1883-1984
Woman's Relief Corps (U.S.). Dept. of Wisconsin
Micro 1151; SC 174; PH 3805; PH 3806
0.2 c.f. (1 folder), 21 reels of microfilm (35mm), 9 photographs, and 9 pieces of ephemera
Wisconsin Historical Society, Library-Archives Division
Records of local Wisconsin chapters of a national women's organization, the auxiliary of the Grand Army of the Republic, established in the state in 1884. Although also concerned with general charitable endeavors and patriotic education, the corps was primarily concerned with aiding veterans and their dependents, particularly those at the Grand Army Home at King, Wisconsin. Microfilmed records include minutes of groups at Columbus, Delavan, Evansville, Fond du Lac, La Crosse, Monticello, Neenah, Omro and other communities, as well as a few charters, financial records, scrapbooks, and correspondence. From the department headquarters there are histories, sample forms, and copies of general orders and circular letters pertaining to Wisconsin. The photographs include images of individuals and groups associated with the Woman's Relief Corps. Also included are holiday cards from the corps, an envelope imprinted with Corps 1090, and a ribbon from a candidate for national president of the Woman's Relief Corps.
The origins of the Woman's Relief Corps, the women's auxiliary of the Grand Army of the Republic, date to the formation of many Christian commissions, sanitary commissions and other relief organizations to which women belonged during the Civil War. During the 1870s the records of the GAR note charity work carried out by women in conjunction with their organization. In 1877 a Woman's Relief Corps was formally organized in Massachusetts as an auxiliary to the GAR in order to aid them in their charitable activities. After several other states followed suit, the GAR authorized a national organization for women in 1881, and an organizational meeting was held in Denver, Colorado in 1883. Unlike the GAR, the organization admitted as members all women committed to its purposes, not just those related to veterans.
The Wisconsin Department of the corps was organized by E. Florence Barker, national president of the Corps, at a meeting in La Crosse in June 1884 of the seven local Wisconsin groups. By 1900 there were 140 corps in the state with a membership of over 5500. A high point in membership was reached shortly after the turn of the century, with 264 posts and 14,000 members.
Like the national organization, the Wisconsin corps were largely concerned with relief activities in behalf of Civil War veterans, widows, and orphans. Gradually their concerns expanded to include Civil War nurses and later to include veterans of all wars. A large part of their efforts went to benefit the Grand Army Home at King, although they also devoted themselves to child welfare, patriotic education, the USO, and anti-drug education. As one of the earliest national organizations for women, the corps also played a role in teaching women about organizational operation and procedure.
As their charitable concerns were assumed by governmental agencies, the Woman's Relief Corps increasingly turned to social activities. By the middle of the twentieth century, the Corps had difficulty in attracting young women, and as the average age of corps members increased many local Wisconsin corps declined and were disbanded.
Additional information concerning the corps and its officers may be found in several unpublished histories included in the collection's materials in paper form (in SC 174).
The records of the Wisconsin Department of the Woman's Relief Corps consist of records of local Wisconsin corps and a small quantity of documentation pertaining to the departmental level of the organization. In addition to this collection, which was processed and microfilmed in 1988, the Society holds the records of several disbanded corps that presented their files to the Historical Society individually. These records had been catalogued as separate collections prior to 1988 and housed at various area research centers. As a result, they were not added to this microfilm collection.
LOCAL CORPS RECORDS primarily consist of minute books returned to the departmental headquarters when local corps disbanded due to declining membership during the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s. For a few local organizations, there are also financial records (sometimes interspersed within the minutes), correspondence, and scrapbooks.
The majority of the local corps are documented only during their last years, but there are long runs for several groups such as Columbus (134, Brown), Delavan (59, Thomas), Evansville (28, Sutphen), Fond du Lac (35, Brown), Monticello (83, Ross), Neenah (101, Lewis), and Omro (94, Sawyer). Also notable, although less extensive are files containing records of the organization's early days such as the records of the Colwell Corps #2 of La Crosse, which was one of the seven founding Wisconsin corps, and the records of the organization in Hillsboro.
DEPARTMENTAL RECORDS consist of several histories of the organization, sample forms, and copies of the published circular letters and general orders which pertained to Wisconsin. Published reports, convention proceedings, and rosters of the Wisconsin department are held by the Society Library.
Printed reports and convention proceedings are available in the Historical Society Library.
Administrative/Restriction Information
Portions presented by Cora Harris, Evansville, Wis., 1958; Mrs. Iva Benson, Evansville, Wis., 1964-1968; Mrs. Nelson C. Hall, Whitefish Bay, Wis., June 12, 1962; Marjorie Holmes, Madison, Wis., April 6, 1967; Mrs. Archie Daggett, Omro, Wis., April 30, 1965; Violet Thiele, Milwaukee, Wis., April 18, 1974; and Earl Monday, April 25, 1986. M64-134, M68-092, M67-136, M65-153, M74-171, M86-169
Contents List
- Department Records
  - Circular letters and general orders, SC 174 (Folder 1)
  - Histories, 1974 (Folder 2)
  - Sample forms (Folder 3)
  - Photographs and ephemera, PH 3805
  - Charters, Micro 1151; See also PH 3805. (Reel 1, Frame 1)
  - Scrapbook for Dept. President Lucille Fink, 1942 (Reel 1, Frame 54)
  - District convention minutes: Districts No. 13, 15, 20-22, 1905-1942 (Reel 1, Frame 147)
- Local Corps Records
  - Post 2, La Crosse (Colwell)
    - Letters, 1883-1890 (Reel 1, Frame 218)
    - Minutes, 1894-1899; 1966-1975 (Reel 1, Frame 286)
    - Scrapbook, circa 1936-1948 (Reel 1, Frame 561)
  - Post 8, Mauston (Northrop): Minutes, 1959-1973 (Reel 1, Frame 574)
  - Post 11, Sheboygan (Wintermeyer)
    - Minutes, 1928-1936; 1978-1982 (Reel 2, Frame 1)
    - History, undated (Reel 2, Frame 242)
  - Post 16, Milwaukee (Wolcott)
    - Minutes, 1966-1968 (Reel 2, Frame 248)
    - Book, 1892 (Reel 2, Frame 273)
      - Original volume, PH 3806
  - Post 23, Milwaukee (Chivas): Minutes, 1898-1902, Micro 1151 (Reel 2, Frame 284)
  - Post 28, Evansville (Sutphen)
    - Minutes
      - 1885-1889; 1896-1903 (Reel 2, Frame 382)
      - 1907-1939 (Reel 3, Frame 1)
      - 1939-1969 (Reel 4, Frame 1)
    - Relief Corps News, 1910 (Reel 4, Frame 519)
  - Post 29, Racine (Harvey): Minutes, 1946-1964 (Reel 5, Frame 1)
  - Post 35, Fond du Lac (Brown): Minutes
    - 1891-1895; 1913-1931; 1940-1942 (Reel 5, Frame 70)
    - 1943-1955 (Reel 6, Frame 1)
  - Post 36, Baraboo (Hooker): Minutes, 1939-1943; 1963-1972 (Reel 6, Frame 305)
  - Post 37, Madison (Fairchild): Minutes, 1973-1978 (Reel 6, Frame 490)
  - Post 41, Kenosha (Lovell): Minutes, 1961-1976 (Reel 6, Frame 552)
  - Post 59, Delavan (Thomas): Minutes
    - 1887-1920 (Reel 7, Frame 1)
    - 1921-1933 (Reel 8, Frame 1)
    - 1934-1938 (Reel 9, Frame 1)
    - 1939-1951; 1964-1984 (Reel 10, Frame 1)
  - Post 61, Menasha (Shepard): Minutes, 1951-1953 (Reel 10, Frame 380)
  - Post 66, Milwaukee (Drake): Minutes, 1960-1966 (Reel 10, Frame 484)
  - Post 67, Rockbridge (McCarthy): Minutes, 1964-1968 (Reel 11, Frame 1)
  - Post 68, Hillsboro (Didiot): Minutes, 1888-1923 (Reel 11, Frame 39)
  - Post 80, Augusta (Perkins): Minutes, 1929-1938 (Reel 12, Frame 1)
  - Post 82, New London (Turner): Minutes, 1973-1982 (Reel 12, Frame 202)
  - Post 83, Monticello (Ross): Minutes
    - 1904; 1911-1924 (Reel 12, Frame 238)
    - 1925-1953; 1969-1984 (Reel 13, Frame 1)
  - Post 86, Clinton (Tallman): Minutes, 1928-1932; 1942-1948 (Reel 14, Frame 1)
  - Post 93, Waupaca (Garfield): Minutes, 1889-1894; 1966-1968 (Reel 14, Frame 167)
  - Post 94, Omro (Sawyer)
    - Minutes
      - 1913-1926 (Reel 14, Frame 293)
      - 1926-1935; 1973-1976 (Reel 15, Frame 1)
    - Reports, 1895-1935 (Reel 15, Frame 239)
    - Cashbooks, 1924-1932 (Reel 15, Frame 362)
  - Post 100, Watertown (Pease): Minutes, 1962-1976 (Reel 15, Frame ???)
  - Post 101, Neenah (Lewis)
    - Minutes
      - 1893-1913; 1915-1924 (Reel 16, Frame 1)
      - 1925-1943 (Reel 17, Frame 1)
      - 1944-1955 (Reel 18, Frame 1)
      - 1955-1964 (Reel 19, Frame 1)
      - 1970-1976 (Reel 20, Frame 1)
      - 1983-1985 (Reel 20, Frame 195)
    - Cashbook, 1971-1985 (Reel 20, Frame 102)
  - Post 108, La Crosse (McKinley): Minutes, 1975-1981 (Reel 20, Frame 229)
  - Post 109, Rice Lake (Heller): Minutes, 1971-1975 (Reel 20, Frame ???)
  - Post 128, Milwaukee (Mueller): Minutes, 1971-1975 (Reel 20, Frame 278)
  - Post 134, Columbus (Brown): Minutes
    - 1901-1924 (Reel 20, Frame 315)
    - 1924-1934 (Reel 21, Frame 1)
  - Post 144, Bloomington (Hickok): Minutes, 1966-1970 (Reel 21, Frame 197)
  - Post 145, Grand Rapids (Wood County): Minutes, 1963-1972 (Reel 21, Frame 266)